<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="zt03116p068.css" type="text/css" charset="UTF-8"?>
<XML>
<TITLE> </TITLE><Body>
<A ID="pgfId-999683"></A>
</Body>
<zootaxaPara>
<A ID="pgfId-1003704"></A>
</zootaxaPara>
<Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1007126"></A>
</Body>
<ZootaxaTitle>
<A ID="pgfId-1010389"></A>
</ZootaxaTitle>
<ZootaxaTitle2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1012156"></A>
</ZootaxaTitle2011>
<ZootaxaTitle2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027010"></A>
Strotihypera, a new Old World genus of the tribe Elaphriini </ZootaxaTitle2011>
<ZootaxaTitle2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027282"></A>
(Lepidoptera, Noctuidae, Noctuinae)</ZootaxaTitle2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027291"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027292"></A>
Vladimir. s. Kononenko1 &amp; Hui-Lin Han2</ZootaxaPara2011>
<zootaxaAddress>
<A ID="pgfId-1027293"></A>
1Laboratory of Entomology, Institute of Biology and Soil Science Far Eastern Branch of Russian Academy of Sciences, RF-690022 Vladivostok, Russia. E-mail: kononenko@ibss.dvo.ru</zootaxaAddress>
<zootaxaAddress>
<A ID="pgfId-1027016"></A>
2School of Forestry, Northeast Forestry University, Harbin, CH-150014 China. E-mail: hanhuilin@yahoo.com.cn</zootaxaAddress>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027017"></A>
</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027319"></A>
</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027018"></A>
Abstract</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027326"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<Abstract>
<A ID="pgfId-1027333"></A>
A new genus Strotihypera gen. n. (type-species Erastria flavipuncta Leech, 1889) is described in the tribe Elaphrriini, subfamily Noctuini from the Eastern Palaearctic. The new combination Strotihypera flavipuncta (Leech, 1889) comb. n. is introduced for Hyperstrotia flavipuncta (Leech, 1889) A review of the Old World genera Strotihypera, Elaphria and Galgula of the tribe Elaphriini is presented.</Abstract>
<Abstract>
<A ID="pgfId-1027019"></A>
</Abstract>
<Abstract>
<A ID="pgfId-1027020"></A>
Key words: Lepidoptera, Noctuidae, Noctuinae, Elaphriini, new genus, new combination, Strotihypera, Elaphria, Galgula, Hyperstrotia, review of genera, Old World, New World</Abstract>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027021"></A>
</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027345"></A>
</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027022"></A>
Introduction</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027023"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027024"></A>
During the last two decades the classification of the higher taxa of the Noctuidae has undergone dramatic modifications. Among other changes, the large heterogeneous assemblage Erastrianae (sensu Hampson 1910), later called Acontiinae (sensu auctorum) has been divided into the subfamilies Acontiinae, Eustrotiinae, Boletobiinae, Aediinae, Metoponiinae and Sinocharinae; some generic complexes were transferred to the subfamily Xyleninae (tribes Elaphriini and Pseudeustrotiini, currently tribes of the subfamily Noctuinae) and to other subfamilies (Speidel et al. 1996; Fibiger &amp; Lafontaine 2005; Lafontaine &amp; Fibiger 2006; Holloway 2009, 2011; Lafontaine &amp; Schmidt 2010; Zahiri et al. 2010). However, the systematic position of some East Palaearctic and Oriental genera or groups of species formerly in Acontiinae (sensu auctorum) have remained uncertain. In particular, type species of some Oriental, Palaearctic and Nearctic taxa have still not been compared, creating uncertaintly in classification of these groups.</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027026"></A>
	In the course of our study of genera of the former subfamily Acontiinae (auct.) we found that the East Palaearctic species “Hyperstrotia” flavipuncta (Leech, 1889), placed in Erastrianae by Hampson (1910) and to Acontiinae (auct.) by Sugi (1982), morphologically does not correspond to any genus of the modern subfamilies derived from Acontiinae (auct.); however, it has well expressed characters of “higher” trifine Noctuidae and has affiliations to Elaphria venustula (Hübner, 1790), which was placed in tribe Elaphriini of the subfamily Xylenini by Fibiger &amp; Hacker (2007), and later in the subfamily Noctuinae by Lafontaine &amp; Schmidt (2010). After examination of the type of <Hyperlink>
<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hype" xml:link="simple" show="replace" actuate="user" CLASS="URL">Hyperstrotia aetheria</A></Hyperlink>
 Grote, 1879, the type-species of the genus Hyperstrotia Hampson, 1910 and other materials kindly sent us by Martin Honey and Don Lafontaine, we have concluded that “Hyperstrotia” flavipuncta is not congeneric with <Hyperlink>
<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperstrotia_aetheria" xml:link="simple" show="replace" actuate="user" CLASS="URL">Hyperstrotia aetheria</A></Hyperlink>
, but belongs to a different genus and subfamily. The structure of genitalia of both sexes of “Hyperstrotia” flavipuncta shows relationships with Elaphriini, while <Hyperlink>
Hyperstrotia aetheria</Hyperlink>
 is placed in the subfamily Phytometrinae by Lafontaine &amp; Schmidt (2010), currently the tribe Phytometrini of the subfamily Boletobiinae (Holloway 2011; Zahiri et al. 2011). Don Lafontaine (pers. comm.) informed us that “Hyperstrotia” flavipuncta does not match any known New World genera of the Elaphriini, although <A ID="OLE_LINK3"></A>
<A ID="OLE_LINK4"></A>
it clearly could be associated with that tribe. </ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027032"></A>
	The new genus Strotihypera gen. n. with type species Erastria flavipuncta Leech, 1889 is described below. Institutional acronyms are as follows: BMNH = Natural History Museum, London; CNC = Canadian National Collection, Ottawa; ZFMK = Zoologisches Forschunginstitut und Museum Alexander Koenig, Bonn.</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027035"></A>
Systematic part</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027036"></A>
</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027037"></A>
Tribe Elaphriini Beck, 1996</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027038"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027039"></A>
Elaphriini Beck, 1996, Neue Entomologische Nachrichten 36: 16. Type-genus Elaphria Hübner, [1818].</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027040"></A>
Synonymy: Galgulina Beck, 1996.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027041"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027042"></A>
Elaphriini is small tribe of the subfamily Noctuinae. It includes small sized moths, characterized by some structure traits of larva (presence of prominent subbasal hump) and genitalia (in the male genitalia costal margin of valva with unsclerotised band in costa, behind costal process; in the female genitalia the posterior part of the 7th segment has a prominent, heavily sclerotised antevaginal crest and ventrally a wrinkled or setose narrow, heavily sclerotised band. The tribe is poorly studied. It includes 10 genera (Galgula Guenée, 1852; Elaphria Hübner, 1818; Anateinoma Möschler, 1890; Bryolymnia Hampson, 1908; Gonodes Druce, 1908; Nolasodes Hampson, 1910; Calymniodes Dognin, 1907; Hampsonides Nye, 1975 Leucosigma Druce, 1908 and Pseudomarimatha Ferris &amp; Lafontaine, 2010) with a total of 208 species; many species are still not described. European taxa of Elaphriini were reviewed by Fibiger &amp; Hacker (2007); New World genus Bryolymnia Hampson, 1908 was revised by Lafontaine et al. (2010) and the genus Pseudomarimatha has been described (Ferris &amp; Lafontaine 2010). Elaphriini has predominantly New World distribution; the majority of species occur in tropical and subtropical regions. Only two genera, Elaphria with four species and Galgula with one species, are known from the Eurasia. Strotihypera is the third Old World genus of the Elaphriini.</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027044"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027371"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027378"></A>
Genus Strotihypera Kononenko &amp; Han, gen. n.</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027045"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027046"></A>
Type-species: Erastria flavipuncta Leech, 1889, Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London 1889: 524, pl. 52: 3 (Type-locality: Japan: Yokohama).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027047"></A>
Hyperstrotia auct.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027048"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027049"></A>
Diagnosis. Small, brown-grey colour moths. Wingspan 18–20 mm. Frons rounded, slightly bulging; hindwing with vein M2 reduced to fold near middle of cell, veins M2 and Cu-A1on common stalk (Fig. 7). In male genitalia: tegumen broad, with enlarger lobes; valva with parallel costal and ventral margins, well developed costa with prominent digitus, and rounded cucullus, without corona; sacculus elongate-moderate, clasper with central position and large, thin, curved harpe about half of valva length. Aedeagus with large apical cornutus about 1/3 length of the aedeagus. In female genitalia: corpus bursae globular anteriorly, gradually tapered posteriorly, with prominent narrow appendix bursae; rather narrow and long, heavily sclerotised; antrum shallow, cup like with sclerotised small antevaginal plate apophyses short and thin, anal papillae small, quadrangular.</ZootaxaPara2011>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027050"></A>
Differential diagnosis. Although Strotihypera does not show prominently expressed Elaphriini characters, it appears to be most closely related to Elaphria (compared with E. venustula (Figs. 2, 8, 12) by wide tegument lobes, structure of pleural sclerites, presence of harpe and digitus with weakly sclerotised patch of valva behind digitus and presence of one large apical cornutus in the aedeagus. It differs from Elaphria by developed costa of the male valva continuously sclerotised to the apex of the valva and pointed apically; developed sclerotised digitus; developed sacculus with position of the clasper in center of valva and presence of rather strong, thin curved harpe about 1/3 of length of valva. Females differ by shallow antrum, small antevaginal plate, narrow and long sclerotised ductus bursae and pyriform shape of the corpus bursae.</zootaxaPara2>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027051"></A>
Description. Adult (Fig. 1). Head with rounded, slightly bulging frons; labial palps curving upward with third segment very small, 3 times smaller than 2nd; antennae filiform, fasciculate; eye moderate, rounded; ocellius present; head and thorax covered with broad flat brown scales; thoracic and abdominal crests present, formed with wide black scales. Legs with spiniform setae confined to tarsi and setae minute; foretibia slightly shorter than femur and tarsus. Forewing venation (Fig. 7) typically quadrifine with Cu vein appearing four branched; forewing rather narrow, with slightly curved costal margin, rounded-angled apex and straight angled tornus; hindwing with typical trifine venation (i.e., M2 reduced to fold near middle of cell). Abdomen without coremata (basal abdominal brushes and pockets). Male genitalia (Fig. 9). Uncus moderate in length, arched, cylindrical, gradually tapered to spine-like, slightly hooked apex; tegumen broad, enlarged into posterior lobe ventrally, about 2 times as wide ventrally as medially; vinculum shorter than tegument, narrow with short distal extensions and narrow V-like saccus; paratergal sclerites broad, recurved; juxta relatively large, heavily sclerotised plate-like, broader anteriorly with central shallow notch posteriorly; valvae symmetrical, rather narrow, with parallel margins, rounded at apex, with indistinct corona formed by row of minute setae; sacculus elongate, with rather broad lobe; apex of sacculus separated by narrow membranous band; clasper positioned in central part of valva, arising from wider base immediately distal to sacculus; harpe large, about 1/3 of length of valva, thin, arched, tipped and slightly curved apically; costa straight, strong, heavily sclerotised, pointed apically, reaching tip of valva, with rather strong acute subapical digitus; ventral margin of valva weakly sclerotised. Aedeagus somewhat curved, smoothly sclerotised with large apical cornutus of about 1/3 length of aedeagus. Female genitalia (Fig. 13). Corpus bursae pyriform, rounded anteriorly, gradually narrower posteriorly into rather wide appendix; ductus bursae rather long, sclerotised, ribbed, straight, twisted and heavily sclerotised in joining with bursae; antrum shallow, wide cup-like, with small rounded antevaginal plate; apophyses posteriores and anterior short thin, equal in length; anal papillae rather small, quadrangular, covered with setae.</zootaxaPara2>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027052"></A>
Distribution &amp; biology. The genus occurs in the Eastern Palaearctic (Manchurian subregion) and northern parts of the Oriental region.</zootaxaPara2>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027053"></A>
Etymology. The generic name Strotihypera is an anagram of Hyperstrotia.</zootaxaPara2>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027054"></A>
Taxonomic note. At present only one species is associated with Strotihypera. However, judging by photographs of imagoes of “Hyperstrotia” rubritincta Wileman &amp; South, 1916, “Hyperstrotia” ochreipuncta (Wileman, 1914) and “Hyperstrotia” macroplaga Hampson, 1907, illustrated by Wang (1995), these may also belong to the genus Strotihypera.</zootaxaPara2>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027055"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027056"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027057"></A>
Strotihypera flavipuncta (Leech, 1889), comb. n.</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027058"></A>
(Figs. 1, 7, 9, 13)</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027059"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027060"></A>
Erastria flavipuncta Leech, 1889, Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London 1889: 524, pl. 52: 3 (Type-locality: Japan: Yokohama [Holotype: BMNH, London].</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027061"></A>
References: Hampson 1910: (Hyperstrotia, Erastrianae); Warren 1913: 277, fig. 52b (Hyperstrotia, Erastrianae); Sugi 1982: 1: 822; 2: 389, pl. 198: 5, 6 (Hyperstrotia, Acontiinae); Poole 1985: 537 (Hyperstrotia); Kononenko et al. 1998: 169, fig. 437 (Hyperstrotia, Acontiinae); Kononenko &amp; Han 2007: 83, pl. 77:1, 228:3 (Hyperstrotia, Eustrotiinae); Kononenko 1990: 10 (Hyperstrotia, Acontiinae); 2003: 259, figs 1, 2 (Hyperstrotia, Acontiinae); 2005: 76 (Hyperstrotia, Eustrotiinae), 2010:19 (Hyperstrotia, Xyleninae).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027062"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027063"></A>
Material examined. 1 male, 2 females, Russia, Primorye terr. Kedrovaya Pad nature reserve, 10–12.vi.1976 (V. Kononenko); 50 specimens, South Korea, Chuncheon, Suwon (CIS, NIAST); 1 male, 1 female, North China, Prov. Jilin, Changbaishan, 25–28.vii.2008 (H.L. Han); 4 males, 3 females, North China, Prov. Liaoning, Anshan, Quianshan Nature park, 5–8.vii.2008 (V. Kononenko).</ZootaxaPara2011>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027064"></A>
Diagnosis. Adult (Fig. 1). No other species in the Old World, except “Hyperstrotia” rubritincta and “Hyperstrotia” ochreipuncta from Taiwan resembles Strotihypera flavipuncta. Wingspan 18–20 mm. Head and thorax covered with wide brown scales; thorax and 1st segment of abdomen with thoracic and abdominal crest, formed by black erected scales. Forewing brown in basal half, grey in terminal half; basal field pale brown, restricted by thin black line; subbasal field brown, darker in costal part, with wide blackish patch formed by erected scales along ventral margin of wing restricted outwardly by clear white and black line; medial field brown, darker than submedial, with clear yellowish-brown spot behind submedial line; orbicular not expressed; antemedial line blackish-brown, twin, with darker and wide inner line; outwardly it bordered with thin pale-greyish line; reniform more or less distinct; postmedial field ash-grey; subterminal field brownish grey, darker than postmedial; dark grey suffusion lies in middle of subbasal and subterminal fields; terminal line thin, blackish, separated for streaks; cilia grey with brown. Hindwing brownish-grey with distinct discal spot; cilia brownish-grey. Male and female genitalia (Figs 9, 13) as described for the genus.</zootaxaPara2>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027065"></A>
Distribution and biology. The species is distributed mainly in the Manchurian subregion of the Palaearctic and partially in the Oriental region, from south of Russian Far East (Primorye and south of Khabarovsk terr., south Sakhalin, south Kuriles) throughout Korea, Japan, China to Taiwan. A mesophilous species that occurs in deciduous forests with Quercus mongolica and Q. dentata in glades, meadows, forest edges, in bushes. It is probably bivoltine, adults flying from early June to August. The larva was illustrated by Mutuura et al. (1965); it feeds on dead and withered leaves of Quercus.</zootaxaPara2>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027066"></A>
Genus Elaphria Hübner, 1818</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027069"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027070"></A>
Elaphria Hübner, 1818, Zuträge zur Sammlung Exotischer Schmettlinge 1: l6. Type-species: Elaphria grata Hübner, 1818 [USA], Florida.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027071"></A>
Synonymy: Agrotis Hübner, 1808, suppr. (ICZN, 1966 Op. 789); Hapalotis Hübner, [1821] 1816; Monodes Guenée, 1852; Carbona Schaus, 1906; Psilomonodes Warren, 1911; Agrotis auct.; Erastria auct.; Mesostrota Möschler, 1890, misspl.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027072"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027073"></A>
Elaphria is a large New World, predominantly Neotropical genus with 127 species; 14 are known from North America, one from Palaearctic, one from China, three from India and one from Africa (Pogue &amp; Bolling 2003). Fibiger &amp; Hacker (2007) listed four Palaearctic species (E. albiviata (Hampson, 1909), E. conjugata (Moore, 1881), E. fissistigma (Hampson, 1898) and E. venustula), however the Old World species, except E. venustula, have never been revised, and placement of these requires confirmation. The main diagnostic features of Elaphria is as <A ID="OLE_LINK5"></A>
<A ID="OLE_LINK6"></A>
referred for the tribe.</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027076"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027409"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027077"></A>
Elaphria venustula (Hübner, 1790)</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027078"></A>
(Figs. 2, 8, 10, 14)</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027079"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027080"></A>
Phalaena Noctua venustula Hübner, 1790, Beiträge zur Geschichte der Schmetterlinge 2 (3): 78, pl. 3 (4): 7 (Type-locality: Germany: Augsburg).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027081"></A>
Synonymy: hybnerana Fabricius, 1794.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027082"></A>
References: Hampson 1909: 493, text fig. 138 (Monodes, Acronyctinae); Warren 1913: 217, fig. 45i (Psilomonodes, Amphipyrinae); Sugi 1982: 1: 821; 2: 384, pl. 197: 69, 68 (Hapalotis, Acontiinae); Chen 1982: 250, fig. 1806 (Monodes, Amphipyrinae); Poole 1985: 353 (Elaphria); Chen, 1999: 769 (Elaphria, Amphipyrinae); Kononenko 1990: 10 (Hapalotis, Acontiinae); 2003: 259, figs 1, 2; 2005: 86 (Elaphria, Acontiinae); 2010:19 (Elaphria, Xyleninae, Elaphriini); Kononenko et al. 1998: 168, fig. 436 (Elaphria, Acontiinae); Fibiger &amp; Hacker 2007: 62, Pl. 2: 86–93, gen. figs. 27, 171 (Elaphria, Xyleninae, Elaphriini); Kononenko &amp; Han 2007: 101, pl. 109:3, 251:2 (Elaphria, Xyleninae, Elaphriini).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027083"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027084"></A>
Material examined. 53 specimens from Europe (France, Hungary, Germany, Denmark), Russia (European part, Ural, West Siberia, Khabarovsk and Primorye terr.), Korea, China, Japan.</ZootaxaPara2011>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027085"></A>
Diagnosis. Adult (Fig. 2). Wingspan 18–22 mm. Frons smooth, rounded, labial palps upturned, 3rd segment is about 2 times shorter than 2nd. Head and thorax and ground colour of forewing white, in fresh specimens with rosy hue; wing pattern with rather large patches of blackish-brown; costal area dark, brownish-grey; the most prominent dark patch is the large triangular ventral one in medial area with large distinct black spot; postmedial line white, orbicular missing, reniform blackish; subterminal field greyish, divided by a white patch by apex; subterminal line diffused, blackish, terminal field blackish-brown, terminal line blackish, diffused; fringes dark grey. Hindwing greyish with weakly traceable postmedial line and discal spot. Coremata presents in base of abdomen. In male genitalia (Fig. 8) uncus relatively stout and short; tegumen broad, with broad penicular lobes; vinculum shorter than tegument, narrow; pleural sclerites plate-like; valva rather long, broader medially; basal half of costa sclerotised, with small traceable digitus; costal margin behind digitus with unsclerotised band; sacculus short, clasper positioned basally, harpe prominent, straight, angled on apical third. Aedeagus short and broad, vesica with large, long, membranous basal diverticulum, bearing large broad-based tapered and pointed cornutus. In female genitalia (Fig. 14) papillae anales moderate, apophyses anteriores and posteriores thin, almost equal in length; 7th abdominal segment with prominent sclerotised antevaginal crest; ductus bursae rather wide, sclerotised, ribbed; corpus bursae ovoid, constricted medially, with large appendix bursae in caudal part.</zootaxaPara2>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027086"></A>
Distribution and biology. A Eurasian species, widely distributed in temperate Palaearctic from Europe, northern Middle East, Ural, throughout south Siberia and Kazakhstan to Russian Far East, Mongolia, China, Korea and Japan. A mesophilous species that occurs in open forest, meadows, and forest-steppe. Two generations per year, the moths flying in late May-June and late July-August. Larvae feed on withered plants of Pothentilla, Rubus, Alchemilla, Genista, and Sarothamnus.</zootaxaPara2>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027875"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="zt03116p068-1.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027876"></A>
Figures 1–8. Imagines. 1. Strotihypera flavipuncta, male, South Korea (NIAST); 2. Elaphria venustula, male, Russia, S Ural (coll. K. Nupponen); 3. Galgula partita, male, Portugal, Madeira (coll. M. Fibiger); 4. Hyperstrotia aetheria, male, USA, Florida (CNC); 5. Hyperstrotia aetheria, female, type of Thalpochares aetheria USA, Florida (BMNH); 6. Ditto, type labels; 7. Strotihypera flavipuncta, wings venation; 8. Elaphria venustula, wings venation</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027880"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="zt03116p068-2.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027881"></A>
Figures 9–12. Male genitalia. 9. Strotihypera flavipuncta, South Korea, genit. prep. 5038 (NIAST); 10. Elaphria venustula, North China, genit. prep. hhl-1281-1 (NEFU); 11. Galgula partita, Portugal, Azores, genit. prep. 5492MF (coll. M. Fibiger); 12. Hyperstrotia aetheria, USA, Florida, genit. prep. 15433.</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027885"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="zt03116p068-3.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027886"></A>
Figures 13–17. Female genitalia. 13. Strotihypera flavipuncta, North China, genit. prep. hhl-1279-2 (NEFU); 14. Elaphria venustula North China, genit. prep. hhl-1280-2 (NEFU); 15. Galgula partita, USA, New York, genit. prep. 5493MF (coll. M. Fibiger); 16. Type of Thalpochares aetheria, USA, Florida, genit prep. 1183 (BMNH); 17. Hyperstrotia aetheria, USA, Florida, genit. prep. 15434 (CNC).</ZootaxaPara2011>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027864"></A>
</zootaxaPara2>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027898"></A>
</zootaxaPara2>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027087"></A>
Taxonomic note. The systematic position of E. venustula has remained uncertain for a long time. It has been placed by authors in either Amphipyrinae or Acontiinae. Its position was fixed in the tribe Elaphriini of the subfamily Xyleninae by Fibiger &amp; Hacker (2007) (currently the tribe Elaphriini in the subfamily Noctuinae; Lafontaine &amp; Schmidt 2010).</zootaxaPara2>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027088"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027089"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027090"></A>
Genus Galgula Guenée, 1852</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027091"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027092"></A>
Galgula Guenée, 1852, in Boisduval &amp; Guenée, Historie Naturelle des Insectes. Species Général des Lépidoptéres. 6: 239. Type-species: Galgula hepara Guenée, 1852, (North America), a junior subjective synonym of Galgula partita Guenée, 1852.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027093"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027094"></A>
Galgula is mostly a New World genus with three described species, distributed predominantly in the Neotropical region. Only G. partita is known from the Old World, and is probably introduced by human activities. The main diagnostic characters are described below in the diagnosis of the species.</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027095"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027434"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027096"></A>
Galgula partita Guenée, 1852</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027097"></A>
(Figs. 3, 11, 15)</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027098"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027099"></A>
Galgula partita Guenée, 1852, in Boisduval &amp; Guenée, Historie Naturelle des Insectes. Species Général des Lépidoptéres 6: 239, (Type-locality North America [Syntypes: BMNH, London].</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027100"></A>
Synonymy: heparca Guenée, 1852; subpartita Guenée, 1852; ferruginea (Walker, 1857); externa (Walker, 1865); novarae (Felder &amp; Rogenhofer, 1874); rorex Möschler, 1886; bias (Druce, 1889); hippodamada (Druce, 1889); mandane (Druce, 1891), interna Barnes &amp; McDunnough, 1917, form.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027101"></A>
References: Hampson 1911: text fig. 122 (Galgula, Acronyctinae); Warren 1913: 217, fig. 50a (Galgula); Poole 1985: 455 (Galgula); Fibiger &amp; Hacker 2007: 61, Pl. 2: 78–85, gen. figs. 26, 170 (Galgula, Xyleninae, Elaphriini).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027102"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027103"></A>
Material examined. 7 specimens from Portugal (Azores) and Spain (Canary Isl.) (coll. M. Fibiger).</ZootaxaPara2011>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027104"></A>
Diagnosis. Adult (Fig. 3). Wingspan 20–26 mm. Frons smooth, rounded; labial palps porrect, the 3rd segment about 1/3 length of the 2nd. Sexually dimorphic. Male forewing colour vary from light brown to dark reddish-brown; in the female – from dark-brown to blackish brown. Wing pattern formed by distinct oblique postmedial line, weakly traceable the lower part of antemedial line, antemedial line of dots and dark interstigmatal patch; orbicular and reniform are indistinct; costal, outer and ventral margins of forewing tinged with brown or dark–brown, fringes pale brown-grey. Hindwing uniformly grey, darker to outer margin. In male genitalia (Fig. 11) uncus upturned, tegument shorter than vinculum; transtilla wide, plate-like; valva rather broad, constricted distally, with large pointed clavus; sacculus broad, clasper with transversal position, harpe bifurcate; costa apically separated from valva; cucullus well developed, looks like an apical flap. Aedeagus moderate, on the left lateral side with long spine-like callus; vesica projecting ventrally, rather broad, subbasally scobinate. In female genitalia (Fig. 15) the 7th segment with prominent heavily sclerotised antevaginal crest and with wrinkled sclerotised band ventrally; ductus bursae short, sclerotised, wrinkled; corpus bursae ovoid with three long ribbon-like signums; appendix bursae sclerotised.</zootaxaPara2>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027105"></A>
Distribution and biology. A Neotropical-Nearctic species with its main distribution in South and North America to southern Canada, and possible anthropogenic distribution in SW Europe. It is known here from the Azores, Canary Islands, England and southern Spain. The species occurs in open warm habitats. The moths fly in several generations from May to October. The larva feeds on Oxalis.</zootaxaPara2>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027106"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027447"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027107"></A>
Genus Hyperstrotia Hampson, 1910</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027108"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027109"></A>
Hyperstrotia Hampson, 1910, Catalogue of the Lepidoptera Phalaenae in the British Museum 10: xvi, 556. Type-species: Thalpochares aetheria Grote, 1879 [USA, Florida] (? = Cryphia nana Hübner, 1818).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027110"></A>
Synonymy: Jaspidia Hübner, 1808, suppr. (ICZN, 1966 Op. 789); Jaspidia Hübner, 1818, unavailable; Protocryphia Barnes &amp; McDunnough, 1918.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027112"></A>
The genus Hyperstrotia, into which Hampson (1910) originally placed two New World and eight Old World species, is currently belongs to the family Erebidae, subfamily Boletobiinae, tribe Phytometrinae (Lafontaine &amp; Schmidt 2010).  However, the results of molecular analysis suggests the Phytometrinae is at best a tribe within the Boletobiinae (D. Lafontaine, pers. comm.; Holloway 2011; Zahiri et al. 2011). Poole (1989) listed ten Old World and six New World species of Hyperstrotia, however Hyperstotia is a heterogeneous assemblage in his concept and requires revision. Some Old World species of Hyperstrotia have already been transferred to other genera: <Hyperlink>
<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperstrotia_inordinata" xml:link="simple" show="replace" actuate="user" CLASS="URL">Hyperstrotia inordinata</A></Hyperlink>
 (Walker, [1863] 1864) to Chorsia Walker, [1863] 1864; <Hyperlink>
<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperstrotia_meeki" xml:link="simple" show="replace" actuate="user" CLASS="URL">Hyperstrotia meeki</A></Hyperlink>
 Bethune-Baker, 1906 and <Hyperlink>
<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperstrotia_molybdota" xml:link="simple" show="replace" actuate="user" CLASS="URL">Hyperstrotia molybdota</A></Hyperlink>
 Hampson, 1910 to Meekstrotia Holloway, 2009 of the subfamily Eustrotiinae (Holloway 2009). In the present article we have already transfered H. flavipuncta to the genus Strotihypera (Elaphriini, Noctuinae). The systematic position of other Old World species (<Hyperlink>
<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki" xml:link="simple" show="replace" actuate="user" CLASS="URL">Hyperstrotia albida</A></Hyperlink>
 Hampson, 1910 [Irak]; <Hyperlink>
<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperstrotia_ochreipuncta" xml:link="simple" show="replace" actuate="user" CLASS="URL">H. ochreipuncta</A></Hyperlink>
 [Taiwan]; <Hyperlink>
<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperstrotia_macroplaga" xml:link="simple" show="replace" actuate="user" CLASS="URL">H. macroplaga</A></Hyperlink>
 [Sri Lanka]; <Hyperlink>
<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperstrotia_semiochrea" xml:link="simple" show="replace" actuate="user" CLASS="URL">H. semiochrea</A></Hyperlink>
 Hampson, 1898 [India]; <Hyperlink>
<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperstrotia_variata" xml:link="simple" show="replace" actuate="user" CLASS="URL">H. variata</A></Hyperlink>
 Wileman &amp; West, 1929 [Philipines]) requires revision.</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027121"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027122"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027123"></A>
Hyperstrotia aetheria (Grote, 1879)</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027124"></A>
(Figs. 4, 5, 12, 16, 17)</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027125"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027126"></A>
Thalpochares aetheria Grote, 1879, North American Entomologist 1: 47 (Type-locality: USA, Florida, Tampa [Holotype: female, BMNH, London].</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027127"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027128"></A>
Material examined. Type of Thalpochares aetheria, female labelled as: Thalpochares aetheria Moore Type/ Grote Coll. 82-54/ Tampa Fla 12.4/Type/ Agrotidae genitalia slide No. 1183 (BMNH, London); 1 male, 1 female, USA, Florida, genit. prep. 15433 male and 15433 female (CNC, Ottawa); 1 female, Florida: Marion Co, Oscala National Forest, Forest Road 97, 0.5 Miles S of SR 316, Sand Pine Schrub, Aug 17 2007, MV Terhune S. Duckel (CNC, Ottawa).</ZootaxaPara2011>
<zootaxaPara2>
<A ID="pgfId-1027129"></A>
Diagnosis. Adult (Figs. 4, 5) Wingspan 18–20 mm. Externally H. aetheria looks somewhat similar to Old World Maliattha spp. (Eustrotiinae). Ground colour of forewing whitish with greyish suffusion in medial part; wing pattern formed by whitish area in costal part and wide oblique greyish suffusion from subapical part of costa to the base of wing; submedial and antemedial lines thin, black; costal area in antemedial and postmedial fields with distinct black marks; lower part of medial, subbasal and basal fields greyish-brown suffusion; orbicular not expressed, reniform as black dot; Subterminal and terminal fields greyish in costal area with whitish dashes; subterminal line as row of black streaks; cilia grey. Hindwing uniformly yellowish-grey. In male genitalia (Fig. 12) tegument high, narrow, uncus thin, moderate; the valves are fused basally, sacculus broad, costa with medial extension; the valves are apically divided. Aedeagus relatively short, with the vesica scobinated and full of pouches. In female genitalia (Figs 16, 17) ovipositor rather broad, apophyses anteriores about 2 times shorter tan anterior ones; antrum with wide antevaginal plate; ductus bursae rather broad, sclerotised; bursa ovoid, filled internally with small spines; ductus seminalis is pigtail-like (characteristic of so many Erebid groups).</zootaxaPara2>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027130"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027472"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027131"></A>
Acknowledgements </ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027132"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027133"></A>
We thank Martin Honey (Natural History Museum, London) for information and presenting photographs of the type of Hyperstrotia aeteria, J. Donald Lafontaine (CNC, Canada) for valuable comments and preparations of male and female genitalia of Hyperstrotia aeteria, and Jocelyn Gill for photographs of adult and genitalia of Hyperstrotia aeteria. The present study was supported by the National Nature Science Foundation of China, No 30700641, the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities, No. DL09CA05 and the special grade of the financial support from China Postdoctoral Science Foundation (No. 200902361), SRF for ROCS, SEM. Kononenko was supported by a grant from the DFG (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft) STU 498/3-1 in 2010-2011 for visiting scientists at ZFMK.</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027134"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027135"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaH1>
<A ID="pgfId-1027136"></A>
References</ZootaxaH1>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027137"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027138"></A>
Chen Y.X. (1982) Iconographia Heterocerorum Sinicorum III. Noctuidae, Agaristidae. Institute zoology Academy sinica. Beijin, pp. 237–390, pls 76–118 (in Chinese).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027139"></A>
<SC1625>
Chen, Y.X. (1999) Lepidoptera: Noctuidae. </SC1625>
<SC1663>
[Fauna Sinica] Insect Vol. 16. </SC1663>
<SC1625>
Beijing, Science press, 1664 pp. </SC1625>
(In Chinese).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027140"></A>
Ferris, C.D. &amp; J.D. Lafontaine (2010) Review of the North American species of Marimatha Walker with descriptions of three new species (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae, Eustrotiinae) and the description of Pseudomarimatha flava (Noctuidae, Noctuinae, Elaphriini), a new genus and species confused with Marimatha. ZooKeys, 39, 117–135.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1028154"></A>
Fibiger, M. &amp; J.D. Lafontaine. (2005) A review of the higher classification of the Noctuoidea (Lepidoptera) – with special reference to the Holarctic fauna. Esperiana, 11, 7–82.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1028155"></A>
Fibiger, M., &amp; H. Hacker (2007) Amphipyrinae - Xyleninae. Noctuidae Europaeae Volume 9. Entomological Press, Sorø, 410 pp.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027143"></A>
Hampson G.F. (1910) Catalogue of the Lepidoptera Phalaenae in the British Museum. Vol. 10, i–xix, 1–829. London, Taylor and Francis.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027144"></A>
Hampson G.F. (1909) Catalogue of the Lepidoptera Phalaenae in the British Museum. Vol. 8, i–xiv, 1–583. London, Taylor and Francis.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027145"></A>
<SC1625>
Holloway, J.D. (2009)</SC1625>
 <SC1625>
The Moths of Borneo, part 13, Family Noctuidae, subfamilies Pantheinae, Bagisarinae, Acontiinae Aediinae, Eustrotiinae, Bryophilinae, Aeroperoninae, Aventiinae, Eublemminae, miscellaneous. Malayan Nature Journal, 62(1–2), 1–240.</SC1625>
</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027970"></A>
Holloway, J.D. (2011) The Moths of Borneo (part 2): families Phaudidae, Himantopteridae and Zygaenidae; revised and annotated checklist. Malayan Nature Journal, 63, 1–548.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027146"></A>
Kononenko, V.S. (1990) Synonymic check list of the Noctuidae (Lepidoptera) of the Primorye Territory, the Far East of U.S.S.R. Tinea, 13 (Supplement 1), 1– 40.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027147"></A>
Kononenko, V. S. (2003) Introduction. Subfamilies Euteliinae, Acontiinae, Acronictinae, Pantheinae, Agaristinae, Amphipyrinae, Cuculliinae, Hadeninae, Noctuinae and Heliothinae. In Lehr P. A. (Ed.) Keys for identification of the insects of the Far East of Russia. Vol. 5. Trichoptera and Lepidoptera. Part 4. Vladivostok, Dal’nauka: 1–34, 215– 217, 237–603 (in Russian).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027148"></A>
Kononenko, V.S. (2005) Noctuidae Sibiricae Vol. 1. An annotated check list of the Noctuidae (s. l. ) (Lepidoptera, Noctuoidae: Nolidae, Erebidae, Micronoctuidae, Noctuidae) of the Asian part of Russia and the Ural region. Entomological Press, Sorø, pp. 1–243.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027149"></A>
Kononenko, V.S. (2010) Noctuidae Sibircae, vol. 2. Micronoctuidae, Noctuidae: Rivulinae – Agaristinae. Entomological Press, Sorø, 475 pp.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1028158"></A>
Kononenko, V.S., Ahn, S.–B. &amp; Ronkay, L. (1998) Illustrated catalogue of Noctuidae in Korea (Lepidoptera). In: K.T. Park (ed.): Insects of Korea, [3], 1– 509.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1028159"></A>
Kononenko, V. S. &amp; Han, H.L. (2007) Atlas genitalia of the Noctuidae in Korea (Lepidoptera). In: Park, K. T. (ed.): Insects of Korea, [11], 464.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1028184"></A>
Lafontaine J.D. &amp; Schmidt, B.C<A ID="OLE_LINK1"></A>
<A ID="OLE_LINK2"></A>
.  (2010) Annotated check list of the Noctuoidea (Insecta, Lepidoptera) of North America north of Mexico. ZooKeys, 40, 1–239.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1028185"></A>
Lafontaine, D.J., Walsh, B., &amp; Holland, R.W. (2010) A revision of the genus Bryolymnia Hampson in North America with descriptions of three new species (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae, Noctuinae, Elaphriini). ZooKeys, 39, 187–204.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027156"></A>
Lafontaine, J.D. &amp; Fibiger, M. (2006) Revised higher classification of the Noctuoidea. Canadian Entomologist, 138, 610–635.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027157"></A>
Mutuura, A., Yamamoto, Y. &amp; Hattori, I. (1979) In: Issiki S. (Ed.). Early stages of Japanese moths incolour. 1. Hoikusha Publishing CO., LTD. 238 pp. (In Japanese).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027159"></A>
Pogue, M. &amp; Sullivan, J.B. <year>
(2003) </year>
Re-evaluation of the Elaphria festivoides (Guenée) species complex(Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington, <volume>
105</volume>
, <pages>
331–347.</pages>
</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027160"></A>
Poole, R.W. (1989) Noctuidae. Lepidopterorum Catalogues (New Series). Fascicle 118, pt 1– 3. 1314 pp., E.J. Brill, Leiden.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027161"></A>
Speidel, W., Fänger, H. &amp; Naumann, C.M. (1996) The phylogeny of the Noctuidae (Lepidoptera). Systematic Entomology, 21, 219–251.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027162"></A>
Sugi, S. (1982) Noctuidae (except Herminiinae). In Inoue H., S. Sugi, H. Kuroko, S. Moriuti, and A. Kawabe. Moths of Japan, 1, 669–913, 2, 334–405, pls. 37, 164–223, 229, 278, 355–280. Kodansha, Tokyo. (In Japanese with English synopsis).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027163"></A>
Wang, H.Y. (1995) Guide book to insects in Taiwan (13). Noctuid moths and it’s allied species from the neighboring countries. Taipei, pp. 1–477 (In Chinese).</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027164"></A>
Warren, W., (1914) in Seitz, A. (Ed.) [1907]–1914 Die Gross–Schmetterlinge der Erde / Macrolepidoptera of theworld. Die Gross–Schmetterlinge des Palaearctischen Faungebietes. Bd 3. Eulenartige Nachtfalter. Stuttgart. Alfred Kernen. i–iv, 511 pp, pls 1–75.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1028260"></A>
Zahiri R., Kitching I.J., Lafontaine J. D., Mutanen, M., Kaila, L., Holloway, J. D. &amp; Wahlberg, N. (2011) A new molecular phylogeny offers hope for a stable family-level classification of the Noctuoidea (Insecta: Lepidoptera). Zoologica Scripta. The Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters, 40, 158–173.</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaRef2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1028261"></A>
Zahiri, R., Holloway, J., Kitching, I.J., Lafontaine, J.D., Mutanen, M. &amp; N. Wahlberg (2011) Molecular phylogenetics of Erebidae (Lepidoptera, Noctuoidea). Systematic Entomology 2011, 1-23, doi: 10.1111/j.1365-3113.2011.00607.x</ZootaxaRef2011>
<ZootaxaPara2011>
<A ID="pgfId-1027166"></A>
</ZootaxaPara2011>
</XML>
